<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Florian Bersier | Blog</title>
 <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com"/>
 <updated>2013-09-15T20:19:15+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://blog.florianbersier.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Florian Bersier</name>
   <email>blah@email.test</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>When Robots Meet the Internet</title>
   <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com/when-robots-meet-internet"/>
   <updated>2013-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.florianbersier.com/when-robots-meet-internet</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Robots generally get a bad role in the movies, travelling back in time to hunt us down or turning against their creators and endangering the Human race. Outside of fiction, robots are still perceived in the collective imagination as a &lt;a href='https://encrypted.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;amp;q=robots%20employment%20threat'&gt;threat to employment&lt;/a&gt;. Such a poor reputation is largely explained by the fear of the unknown and the difficulty to apprehend the whys and wherefores of robotics. Hopefully, things are about to change and the Internet is probably going to be the driving force behind the evolution of mindsets and the demystification of robots. The Internet and more precisely the Internet of Things indeed propose tools and protocols that can tackle efficiently key challenges for the development and democratization of robotics, i.e. object recognition, information processing and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet is continuously being supplied with eyes and ears, but it still misses arms and legs to take action! [&amp;#8230;] Robots seem the logical candidates that take on the role of gateways of information flows. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; CFP for &lt;a href='http://www.theinternetofthings.eu/prepublication-robotics-meets-internet-things-soon-be-cfp'&gt;Cloud Robotics and the Internet of Things&lt;/a&gt; (2012)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post starts with a brief definition and some illustrations of what is the Internet of Things. Then I move to the identification and description of three crucial axes for the development of robotics, namely object recognition, information processing and control. The raison-d&amp;#8217;être of this section is to share some insights concerning the way the Internet and IoT could provide interesting and natural answers to the latter dimensions. I conclude by highlighting some points that might endanger the sustainability of an environment made of Internet-powered/aware robots, that is a lack of standardization and integration, (cloud) data privacy concerns, the risk of technological &amp;#8220;solutionism&amp;#8221; and vague human-robots interaction laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='internet_of_things_iot'&gt;Internet of Things (IoT)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No need to define what is the Internet, or more precisely, what is the first version of the Internet, that is a global system of interconnected computer networks which makes available thanks to a specific protocol (&lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_protocol_suite'&gt;TCP/IP&lt;/a&gt;) a growing amount of data created by human beings. The Internet of Things is sometimes described as the next version of the Internet and is all about data created by things. As its name indicates, the Internet of Things (IoT hereafter) refers to physical and uniquely identifiable objects (or things) that are connected to the Internet and are so able to identify themselves to other devices and to communicate with them. In other words, IoT moves the boundaries of the information system from the online world to the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like something out of a sci-fi movie, the Internet of Things promises to transform our daily lives. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; Daniel Saks, AppDirect &lt;a href='http://www.wired.com/insights/2013/03/faster-please-breaking-down-barriers-to-the-internet-of-things/'&gt;in Wired&lt;/a&gt; (2013)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, IoT mainly rests on Radio-frequency identification (&lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RFID'&gt;RFID&lt;/a&gt;), i.e. the wireless non-contact use of radio-frequency electromagnetic fields to transfer data, in order to identify and track tags attached to objects. For instance, RFID tags can report sensor data such as motion, temperature or humidity, identification data (e.g. biometric passports) and so on and so forth. Note that IoT also commonly uses barcodes and other 2D-codes (e.g. &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qr_code'&gt;QR codes&lt;/a&gt;) for identification purposes. Another crucial (coming) technological feature of IoT is the unique adressability of things, meaning that every object is identified by a singular IP address. Thanks to the &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6'&gt;IPv6 protocol&lt;/a&gt; and its extremely large address space (roughly 2&lt;sup&gt;128&lt;/sup&gt; IP addresses), this won&amp;#8217;t be too much of a problem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='a_few_examples'&gt;A Few Examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An over-used and quite limited (to not say dumb) illustration of IoT is the &amp;#8221;&lt;a href='http://fuckyeahinternetfridge.tumblr.com/'&gt;smart fridge&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;, or the fact to have a fridge able to notify you when you run out of milk and even order some if needed. Instead of talking about fridges, I focus in the coming lines on three different IoT-related products and ideas I find convincing and promising. The first example highlights the ability for objects to communicate between each others, the second one shows how things can become smart and autonomous, and the third and last example provides a meaningful illustration of what sensors-powered objects can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id='i_automatic__your_car_and_smartphone_connected'&gt;i) &lt;a href='http://www.automatic.com/'&gt;Automatic&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; Your Car and Smartphone, Connected&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nota Bene: To play/pause a video, just click on it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder='0' height='315' src='http://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/_AyXNeRbpRk?wmode=transparent;rel=0;showinfo=0;controls=0' width='560'&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The device [Automatic] combines two burgeoning trends—the &amp;#8220;Internet of things&amp;#8221;, where traditionally offline gadgets are connected to the Internet to amplify their usefulness, and the mining of data that&amp;#8217;s collected by our devices for meaning. By putting these two together, the company thinks it can get users to conserve gas and spend less—and make a profit itself while doing so. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://www.technologyreview.com/news/512211/gadget-gets-under-the-hood-to-bring-analytics-to-driving/'&gt;MIT Technology Review&lt;/a&gt; (2013)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id='ii_nest__the_learning_thermostat'&gt;ii) &lt;a href='http://www.nest.com/'&gt;Nest&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; The Learning Thermostat&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder='0' height='315' src='http://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/L8TkhHgkBsg?wmode=transparent;rel=0;showinfo=0;controls=0' width='560'&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nest is a game changer. [&amp;#8230; It] learns from user behavior and eventually adjusts the home&amp;#8217;s climate control based on previous activity. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://techcrunch.com/2011/12/22/nest-arm-zigbee/'&gt;TechCrunch&lt;/a&gt; (2011)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id='iii_myo__the_gesture_control_armband'&gt;iii) &lt;a href='https://getmyo.com/'&gt;MYO&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; The Gesture Control Armband&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder='0' height='315' src='http://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/oWu9TFJjHaM?wmode=transparent;rel=0;showinfo=0;controls=0' width='560'&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like Minority Report, but better: the MYO armband will let you control iTunes by snapping your fingers, command radio-controlled toys like Luke using the Force, and flash through Powerpoint presentations without using a clicker. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://www.technologyreview.com/view/512016/can-a-myoelectric-armband-replace-your-mouse/'&gt;MIT Technology Review&lt;/a&gt; (2013)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id='irobot'&gt;I-Robot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section is interested in showing how the Internet in general and IoT in particular will occupy an increasingly prominent role in the future of robotics, eventually leading to the coming of Internet-powered robots (I-Robots henceforth). Three crucial challenges for the development of robots are identified and presented, that is object recognition, information processing and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='object_recognition'&gt;Object Recognition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Object recognition is a key unresolved challenge for robotics. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; Michahelles, van Kranenburg and Waibel, &lt;a href='http://www.rfidjournal.com/articles/view?9773'&gt;RFID Journal&lt;/a&gt; (2012)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robots are by definition autonomous systems that need to interact with their specific environments. The latter observation implies that they must be able to recognize the physical objects surrounding them in a first stage in order to take appropriate actions in a second stage. Nowadays, object recognition is mainly achieved through image recognition, i.e. diverse algorithms extract specific object features from a video stream or single image and compare them with other objects sharing the same features stored in a database. Unnecessary to emphasize that such a process is both costly in terms of computations and error-prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IoT proposes a completely different way of dealing with object recognition. By making objects &amp;#8220;smart&amp;#8221; and connected, robots don&amp;#8217;t have to identify objects around them since objects automatically identify themselves to robots. To illustrate this, let&amp;#8217;s consider a very trivial example: a robot whose unique function is to prepare your wake up coffee. In such a case, object recognition could be used to track the robot&amp;#8217;s position in the kitchen, to identify a coffee mug or the coffee pot&amp;#8217;s handle via tags, e.g. a barcode indicating that the object is a mug with a specific capacity in centiliters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An existing and early application of IoT-capable robots is the one developed on a large scale by &lt;a href='http://www.kivasystems.com/'&gt;Kiva Systems&lt;/a&gt;. This company, recently acquired by Amazon, proposes warehouse robots that use QR codes to sense their locations (see video below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder='0' height='315' src='http://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/QhfDKeDUvbE?wmode=transparent;rel=0;showinfo=0;controls=0' width='560'&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that more and more objects i) will be connected to the Internet (e.g. through a wireless home network), ii) will use a common protocol to communicate and interact, iii) or will be tagged (e.g. barcodes) may sound strange and unrealistic in 2013 but this won&amp;#8217;t be the case in a few years from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='information_processing'&gt;Information Processing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A robot is a machine that gathers information about its environment and uses that information to follow instructions to do some sort of work. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://www.thetech.org/'&gt;The Tech Museum of Innovation&lt;/a&gt; (2000)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tech Museum&amp;#8217;s definition of robots is especially interesting because it emphasizes well the vital role played by information and information processing in robotics. Indeed, robots are &amp;#8220;intellingent&amp;#8221; systems who continuously treat and process data to achieve tasks they have been designed for. And more complex the tasks, more important is the amount of information to process, leading inevitably to heavier computations and larger costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a significant part of these computations does not need to take place in real-time, and it&amp;#8217;s where the Internet can help. By moving to the &lt;a href='http://cdn.thenextweb.com/wp-content/blogs.dir/1/files/2012/12/Grishin-Final-SB.jpg'&gt;cloud&lt;/a&gt; actions without hard real-time requirements, the computing power on the robot is reduced, improving then operation duration of systems and decreasing costs. For instance, a common high-level robotics task which does not require hard real-time is called &amp;#8220;mapping&amp;#8221;. Mapping is the fact to store a description of the environment to allow a robot to localize a landmark or itself, e.g. this can go from trajectories planning to object grabbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two other obvious advantages of offloading computation to the cloud are that such a centralization can foster collaboration and simplify software updates. For example, if robots share the same clouding platform, they could build a common map, and some of their functions could be updated directly from the cloud like a smartphone&amp;#8217;s application, e.g. &lt;a href='http://www.robotappstore.com/'&gt;RobotAppStore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initiatives like &lt;a href='http://www.roboearth.org/what-is-roboearth'&gt;RoboEarth&lt;/a&gt;, a &amp;#8220;World Wide Web for robots&amp;#8221;, all together with its recent protocol or &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PaaS'&gt;PaaS&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href='http://rapyuta.org/rapyuta-the-roboearth-cloud-engine'&gt;Rapyuta&lt;/a&gt; (see video below) are concrete illustrations of cloud robotics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder='0' height='315' src='http://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/4-ir1ieqKyc?wmode=transparent;rel=0;showinfo=0;controls=0' width='560'&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes no doubt that cloud computing will be a key factor in the democratization of robots, decreasing their cost of production and maintenance, while increasing their &amp;#8220;knowledge&amp;#8221; and computing capacity thanks to collaboration and centralization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='control'&gt;Control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A robot may not injure a human being or, through inaction, allow a human being to come to harm.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;A robot must obey any orders given to it by human beings, except where such orders would conflict with the First Law.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;A robot must protect its own existence as long as such protection does not conflict with the First or Second Law. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; Isaac Asimov, &amp;#8220;I, Robot&amp;#8221;, &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Laws_of_Robotics'&gt;The Three Laws of Robotics&lt;/a&gt; (1941)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet already has and will have a growing importance in the way humans control robots. In this section, I consider three different dimensions, depending on the features of human-robot interactions (HRI). Please also note that as a matter of personal preference, the word &amp;#8220;communication&amp;#8221; is used instead of &amp;#8220;control&amp;#8221; in the next lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id='hard_communication'&gt;Hard Communication&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I define hard communication as the fact to communicate with an I-Robot using a physical or hard object connected to the Internet, e.g. a smartphone, a tablet, a laptop, some &lt;a href='http://www.google.com/glass/start/what-it-does/'&gt;Google&amp;#8217;s glasses&lt;/a&gt; or IoT-capable items. Assuming that more and more robots and things will be connected to the Internet, hard communication will become increasingly important. For instance, we will communicate with a robot present in our home while we are away via a specific application installed on our smartphones. By making communication between a robot and a human as easy as a touch on a screen via pre-configured software, this type of communication will certainly democratize the use of robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early and fun illustration of hard communication is proposed by LEGO with its &amp;#8221;&lt;a href='http://mindstorms.lego.com/en-us/default.aspx'&gt;Mindstorms&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; (see video below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder='0' height='315' src='http://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RHdiBvpq7Dg?wmode=transparent;rel=0;showinfo=0;controls=0' width='560'&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h4 id='soft_communication'&gt;Soft Communication&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soft communication regroups Internet technologies which allow more natural or softer ways to communicate with robots. Specifically, soft communication is close to the field of artificial intelligence (&lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI'&gt;AI&lt;/a&gt;). The main idea here is that cloud robotics will increase the amount of data available to robots, making them &amp;#8220;smarter&amp;#8221; and so more prone to interact and communicate with humans in a soft way. For example, text-to-speech (&lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Text_to_speech'&gt;TTS&lt;/a&gt;) technology is promised to a bright future in robotics, robots being able to understand, interpret and reply to requests when we will talk to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id='raw_communication'&gt;Raw Communication&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I define raw communication as the fact to communicate with robots using programming languages. This is the raw basis of every kind of HRI. Here, the introduction of IoT and cloud computing into robotics will surely have important effects on the type of languages (e.g. Python) and data formats (e.g. JSON) robots will rest on, encouraging the adoption of tools and methods already commonly used by Web developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coming generation of I-Robots will also certainly encourage the creation of new &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/API'&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;s, e.g. to facilitate the communication between robots and diverse IoT objects. Finally, we can expect to observe a growing enthusiasm for the development and sharing of robot-targeted scripts on platforms like &lt;a href='https://github.com/'&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, constantly increasing the possibilities and fonctionalities of our beloved autonomous systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='challenges__future_directions'&gt;Challenges &amp;amp; Future Directions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen that the Internet can foster the development and democratization of robotics in many respects. Specifically, IoT provides a completely different way of dealing with object recognition, by making key objects in our daily lives capable of communicating with autonomous systems. Cloud computing decreases the amount of computations that a robot needs to do on its own by centralizing a consequent part of data and calculations in the cloud, encouraging so collaboration and facilitating software maintenance. Finally, the Internet transforms the way we communicate with robots, by making control easier, more natural and more open. To be concise and to summarize, the Internet provides a promising new platform for the development of smarter and cheaper robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if we want these changes to be viable and sustainable in the long run, there are a few challenges ahead we need to be aware of and willing to deal with, namely standardization, data privacy, technological solutionism and legal framework for HRI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='standardization'&gt;Standardization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, IoT would rest on a unique &amp;#8220;API&amp;#8221;, allowing every object connected to the Internet to communicate and to interact with other ones using a common &amp;#8220;language&amp;#8221;. Now, this is far from reality. The Internet of Things is an emerging market, and current IoT companies all propose products that use their own specific protocol. If things go on like that, we will end up with a situation where Internet-capable things from company X will be able to communicate between themselves but won&amp;#8217;t be capable of interacting with objects from company Y or company Z, limiting then the promises and possibilities of the Internet [of Things].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id='one_api_to_rule_them_all'&gt;One API to rule them all?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main challenge we&amp;#8217;re facing is that unlike the creation of the Web, the development of IoT is primarily businness driven. The Internet favorizing a &amp;#8220;winner-takes-the-most&amp;#8221; market structure, this implies that a very few IoT companies will be the unquestioned leaders of this sector in a few years from now. Knowing this, some different scenarios could lead to the emergence of a standard. For instance, if one or several of the latter companies would decide to make their API open-source at a certain point of time, this could encourage start-ups active in the Internet of Things to adopt it, independent developers to write scripts based on it and so on&amp;#8230; leading eventually to the birth of a sound and major standard controlled by an independent and international organization, like the &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/W3C'&gt;W3C&lt;/a&gt; for the Web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='data_privacy'&gt;Data Privacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly any time you have something autonomous or semi-autonomous, you should worry about who controls it. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; Bruce Schneier, author of &lt;a href='http://www.schneier.com/book-lo.html'&gt;Liars and Outliers&lt;/a&gt; - in &lt;a href='http://thenetwork.cisco.com/'&gt;The Network&lt;/a&gt; (2013)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming years, the Internet of Things and Cloud Robotics will clearly produce a lot more information about ourselves, our consumption, our habits, etc. While the &amp;#8220;data privacy &amp;amp; security&amp;#8221; topic is not new at all, it seems important to make people sensitive to the fact that the dimensions and completeness of information stored about themselves will grow exponentially in the next few years. We will need to accompany this new dynamics with a continuing and increasing legal and technological effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='technological_solutionism'&gt;Technological Solutionism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;#8230;] A pervasive and dangerous ideology that I call &amp;#8220;solutionism&amp;#8221;: an intellectual pathology that recognizes problems as problems based on just one criterion: whether they are &amp;#8220;solvable&amp;#8221; with a nice and clean technological solution at our disposal. Thus, forgetting and inconsistency become &amp;#8220;problems&amp;#8221; simply because we have the tools to get rid of them — and not because we&amp;#8217;ve weighed all the philosophical pros and cons. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; Evgeny Morozov in &lt;a href='http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/03/opinion/sunday/the-perils-of-perfection.html/'&gt;The New York Times&lt;/a&gt; (2013)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.evgenymorozov.com/'&gt;Morozov&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;s solutionism is somehow linked to the code of ethics we need to keep in mind whenever creating or developing a new technology. Put differently, technological progress should be always envisaged in terms of &lt;a href='http://market.subwiki.org/wiki/Social_surplus'&gt;social surplus&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. the overall value of a technology for the whole society and not only for a given group of individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='legal_framework_for_humanrobot_interactions'&gt;Legal Framework for Human-Robot Interactions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides ethics, we will need to think of an efficient legal framework in order to accompany a new environment and a new kind of interactions between machines and human beings. Murphy and Woods revisited in 2009 the legendary three &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Laws_of_Robotics'&gt;laws of robotics&lt;/a&gt; first proposed by Asimov in the 1940s, and called them &amp;#8220;The Three Laws of Responsible Robotics&amp;#8221;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A human may not deploy a robot without the human-robot work system meeting the highest legal and professional standards of safety and ethics.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;A robot must respond to humans as appropriate for their roles.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;A robot must be endowed with sufficient situated autonomy to protect its own existence as long as such protection provides smooth transfer of control which does not conflict with the First and Second Laws.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those could represent a good start&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='short_conclusion'&gt;Short Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No doubt that the Internet and robots are made to evolve together. By the end of the decade, their technological symbiosis will have significantly transformed our daily lives. Let&amp;#8217;s just hope that we will do everything to ensure that such an important and promising technological progress will benefit to the whole Humankind&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robots will naturally interact with people both physically and cognitively based on advanced communication and information processing – in all areas of our lives. Robotics will be a key element for dealing with societal challenges Europe is facing. From ageing society, to creation and retention of jobs, growing security threats and increasing worldwide competition for production sites - robotics is a solution provider. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://www.eurobotics-project.eu/press-room/eurobotics-press-releases/robots-save-jobs-in-europe.html'&gt;EU Robotics&lt;/a&gt; (2011)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the word robot will disappear, the point of acceptance [will be] when [we will] stop thinking of robots as robots and just in terms of functionality. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8211; Sabine Hauert, &lt;a href='http://videos.liftconference.com/video/1178752/sabine-hauert-robotics-today?player_id=1176439'&gt;Lift Conference&lt;/a&gt; (2011)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Credits: Banner picture from the movie &quot;I, Robot&quot; (2004), © 20th Century Fox.&lt;/em&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>I Know Who You are!</title>
   <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com/i-know-who-you-are"/>
   <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.florianbersier.com/i-know-who-you-are</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, your daily browsing activity is stored, aggregated, analysed and sold for advertising purposes by Internet companies, e.g. Gmail &lt;a href='https://mail.google.com/mail/help/intl/en_GB/more.html#scanning'&gt;scans your emails&lt;/a&gt; to deliver &amp;#8220;targeted&amp;#8221; ads, Facebook &lt;a href='http://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/05/opinion/sunday/facebook-is-using-you.html?pagewanted=all&amp;amp;_r=0'&gt;serves ads&lt;/a&gt; depending on your relationship status or interests, etc. No big news here! What is less known is how your browser can reveal a sensible amount of information about yourself. This post aims at highlighting and describing the diverse types of data websites can quite easily gather just by &amp;#8220;sniffing&amp;#8221; your browser, and how these information once all wired together can help recompose a significant part of who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='i_know_where_you_live'&gt;I know where you live&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your computer, tablet or smartphone connects to a website, it leaves a log of its public &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Protocol'&gt;IP address&lt;/a&gt;. This is because the website needs your IP in order to make the connection between its server and your machine and then send the web pages you requested. All the existing IP addresses are assigned in blocks and publicly registered to specific Internet Service Providers (ISPs) or other organizations (universities, governments, corporations, etc.), making easy their access and their classification depending on geographical parameters. Today, several independent companies have created large databases linking a specific IP address to its respective country, city, region, ISP. To check it by yourself, visit &lt;a href='http://www.ip-tracker.org/'&gt;this service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it is extremely simple for a developer to retrieve the IP address of a visitor and translate it into geographical attributes. For instance, the following snippet uses jQuery and the &lt;a href='http://www.wipmania.com/en/api/'&gt;Wipmania API&lt;/a&gt; to find out the country associated to the IP address of a visitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;IP-based Geolocation&lt;/code&gt;&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='na'&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.8.3/jquery.min.js&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nx'&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;getJSON&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;http://api.wipmania.com/jsonp?callback=?&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Ajax call powered by jQuery&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;country&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;country&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// get Country associated to the IP address&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class='nx'&gt;alert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;country&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='p'&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id='tip_not_comfortable_with_that_use_proxies_or_become_anonymous_thanks_to_tor'&gt;Tip: Not comfortable with that? Use proxies or become anonymous thanks to &lt;a href='https://www.torproject.org'&gt;TOR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h2 id='i_know_which_language_you_speak'&gt;I know which language you speak&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your browser makes easily available the language in which it is configured. It is pretty common in web development to retrieve this piece of information to serve targeted content depending on the language of the visitor, e.g. currency, default language. The following snippet of code written in JavaScript detects the language code and translates it into human-readlable form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Language Detection&lt;/code&gt;&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='javascript'&gt;&lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Detect language of the browser&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;language&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userLanguage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 

&lt;span class='c1'&gt;// translate language code to actual language&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;en&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;English&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;de&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;German&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;it&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Italian&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;fr&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;French&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;es&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Spanish&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;cn&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Chinese&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;gr&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Greek&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;pl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Polish&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;jp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Japanese&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;in&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Indian&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;ru&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Russian&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
		&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;kr&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;lang&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;Korean&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;span class='c1'&gt;// and so on and so forth...&lt;/span&gt;
 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id='i_know_what_technology_youre_using'&gt;I know what technology you&amp;#8217;re using&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Browser interrogation, or the fact to gather as much data as possible about the configuration of your machine, makes browser tracking and device fingerprinting possible. It is important to understand how this sniffing process can help companies or individuals track and follow you around the web thanks to the precise information they have gathered about your machine, e.g. operating system, browser, browser version, screen resolution and plugins installed. It turns out that a machine&amp;#8217;s configuration tends to be highly unique and easily accessible even if the browser’s cookies are deleted. Not convinced? Feel free to perform this &lt;a href='http://panopticlick.eff.org/'&gt;nice test&lt;/a&gt; provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the logics behind this, here are some lines of JavaScript that get the browser, browser version and operating system of a visitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Browser Interrogation&lt;/code&gt;&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='javascript'&gt;&lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;BrowserDetect&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;init&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;browser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;searchString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataBrowser&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;||&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;An unknown browser&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;version&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;searchVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;||&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;searchVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;appVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;||&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;an unknown version&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;searchString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataOS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;||&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;an unknown OS&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;searchString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='k'&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='mi'&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataString&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataProp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;prop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearchString&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;||&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class='p'&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataProp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='p'&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;searchVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;indexOf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearchString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='k'&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nb'&gt;parseFloat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;substring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearchString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;length&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='mi'&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataBrowser&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;[{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Chrome&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Chrome&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;OmniWeb&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;OmniWeb/&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;OmniWeb&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;vendor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Apple&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Safari&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Version&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;prop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nb'&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;opera&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Opera&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Version&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;vendor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;iCab&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;iCab&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;vendor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;KDE&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Konqueror&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Firefox&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Firefox&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;vendor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Camino&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Camino&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// for newer Netscapes (6+)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Netscape&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Netscape&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;MSIE&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Explorer&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;MSIE&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Gecko&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Mozilla&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;rv&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// for older Netscapes (4-)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Mozilla&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Netscape&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;versionSearch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Mozilla&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;}],&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;dataOS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;[{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;platform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Win&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Windows&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;platform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Mac&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Mac&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;userAgent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;iPhone&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;iPhone/iPod&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;navigator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;platform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;subString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Linux&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;identity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Linux&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;}]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='p'&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Initialization Browser sniffing&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nx'&gt;BrowserDetect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;init&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Operating system&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;os&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;BrowserDetect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Browser&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;browser&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;BrowserDetect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;browser&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Browser version&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;version&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;BrowserDetect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the browser detected, let&amp;#8217;s say Google Chrome, we can retrieve the extensions installed via small scripts such as the one proposed by &lt;a href='http://blog.kotowicz.net/2012/02/intro-to-chrome-addons-hacking.html'&gt;Kotowicz.net&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='i_know_your_browsing_habits'&gt;I know your browsing habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another crucial type of information developers can gather is the websites you tend to visit regularly. There exist a few different methods to achieve this. One smart exploit I am going to present here detects the websites in which a visitor is logged in via the authenticated images event handler. The method is straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assume a specific image, e.g. https://example.com/img.png, is only accessible if the browser is currently logged into https://example.com. If the browser is not signed-in when I instruct the browser to make the Web request, the image will obviously not be returned. If the browser is signed-in, the image will be returned normally. Based upon this binary behavior, I can detect the difference between a logged-in and not logged-in browser, and by attaching a small bit of Javascript to the IMG tag, can return that information to my site. For example, the following code detects if a visitor is logged into Facebook, Google and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Login Detection&lt;/code&gt;&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;FacebookStatus&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;outputStatus&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;TwitterStatus&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;outputStatus&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;GmailStatus&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;outputStatus&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;GooglePlusStatus&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;outputStatus&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Google --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;style=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;display:none;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='na'&gt;onload=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;show_login_status(&amp;#39;Gmail&amp;#39;, true)&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='na'&gt;onerror=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;show_login_status(&amp;#39;Gmail&amp;#39;, false)&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='na'&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;https://accounts.google.com/CheckCookie?continue=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com%2Fintl%2Fen%2Fimages%2Flogos%2Faccounts_logo.png&amp;amp;followup=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com%2Fintl%2Fen%2Fimages%2Flogos%2Faccounts_logo.png&amp;amp;chtml=LoginDoneHtml&amp;amp;checkedDomains=youtube&amp;amp;checkConnection=youtube%3A291%3A1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;style=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;display:none;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='na'&gt;onload=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;show_login_status(&amp;#39;GooglePlus&amp;#39;, true)&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='na'&gt;onerror=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;show_login_status(&amp;#39;GooglePlus&amp;#39;, false)&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='na'&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;https://plus.google.com/up/?continue=https://www.google.com/intl/en/images/logos/accounts_logo.png&amp;amp;type=st&amp;amp;gpsrc=ogpy0&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Twitter --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;style=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;display:none;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='na'&gt;onload=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;show_login_status(&amp;#39;Twitter&amp;#39;, true)&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class='na'&gt;onerror=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;show_login_status(&amp;#39;Twitter&amp;#39;, false)&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='na'&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;https://twitter.com/login?redirect_after_login=%2Fimages%2Fspinner.gif&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Facebook&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class='nb'&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;fbAsyncInit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class='nx'&gt;FB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;init&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;({&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;appId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;XXXX&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='kc'&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class='nx'&gt;cookie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='kc'&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;xfbml&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='kc'&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;});&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Your App id&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class='nx'&gt;FB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;getLoginStatus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;response&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;response&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;status&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;unknown&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nx'&gt;show_login_status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Facebook&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kc'&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class='p'&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nx'&gt;show_login_status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Facebook&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kc'&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class='p'&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class='p'&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class='p'&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Load the SDK Asynchronously&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;facebook-jssdk&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='k'&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;createElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;script&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;async&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kc'&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;//connect.facebook.net/en_US/all.js&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class='nx'&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;getElementsByTagName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;head&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;appendChild&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class='p'&gt;}(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nb'&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Results&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;show_login_status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;network&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
         &lt;span class='nx'&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;#&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;network&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Status&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;You are currently logged in to &amp;lt;span class=&amp;#39;red&amp;#39;&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;network&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class='p'&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='k'&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
         &lt;span class='nx'&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;#&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;network&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;Status&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;You are not currently logged in to &amp;lt;span class=&amp;#39;green&amp;#39;&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;network&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class='p'&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class='p'&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remark that the same methodology can be applied for CSS or JS files, iframes&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id='tip_not_comfortable_with_that_disable_3rdparty_cookies_in_your_browsers_settings_it_helps_use_private_browsing_firefox__ie_or_incognito_chrome_modes_as_often_as_you_can'&gt;Tip: Not comfortable with that? Disable 3rd-party cookies in your browser&amp;#8217;s settings, it helps. Use Private Browsing (Firefox &amp;amp; IE) or Incognito (Chrome) modes as often as you can.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h2 id='ok_lets_make_a_break'&gt;OK, let&amp;#8217;s make a break&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before to go further, let&amp;#8217;s check what type of information can be retrieved from your browser. Here is a simple demo I&amp;#8217;ve put in place to illustrate this post: &lt;a href='http://play.florianbersier.com/who-are-you/'&gt;START DEMO »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By sniffing your browser, I can easily gather information about your location (IP), language (browser language and IP), get a very precise idea of the software - and even hardware - you&amp;#8217;re using (browser interrogation), attach an ID to your machine and track you (browser interrogation), and get a good picture of your browsing habits (e.g., login detection).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact to access this kind of raw data is not terribly severe&amp;#8230; if taken separately. However, if wired together and computed by algorithms resting on global empirical data, it then becomes possible to infer more sensible information about yourself. For instance, knowing your browsing activity and machine&amp;#8217;s configuration, I can get an idea of your age and determine whether there is a higher probability for you to be a male or a female (see figures below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt='Facebook Wall-to-Wall Conversation' src='http://royal.pingdom.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/social-network-gender-distr-580px.jpg' /&gt;&lt;img alt='Facebook Wall-to-Wall Conversation' src='http://royal.pingdom.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/social-network-age-distribution-580px.jpg' /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, given your location, machine&amp;#8217;s configuration and browsing habits, I can get insights about your income level or education. For instance, according to a &lt;a href='http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304458604577488822667325882.html'&gt;study realized by Orbitz in 2012&lt;/a&gt;, Mac users spend as much as 30% more a night on hotels than PC users. Not bad, eh?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: No need to be Google or Facebook to have a good idea of who you are. Surely, the granularity of information gathered from your browser is not comparable to the one proposed by big current Internet players. However, you should be aware that smart or even malicious websites have the means to access more sensible data about yourself than you would ever imagine. To be short, web browsers do NOT protect your privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Facebook Fail</title>
   <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com/facebook-bug"/>
   <updated>2012-09-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.florianbersier.com/facebook-bug</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Facebook faced yesterday (September 24, 2012) one of the biggest critical situations of its history, a trust-based crisis due to old posts featuring potentially some intimate information made easily visible on Facebook profiles, or Timelines. The origin of this situation is not technical but comes mainly from the Facebook&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;usual&amp;#8221; lack of prospectiveness concerning the concept of privacy. Now, such an eye-opening experience was necessary both for the company and its users, and some lessons should be clearly learned here. But will they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='the_facts'&gt;The Facts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href='http://www.metrofrance.com/high-tech/facebook-d-anciens-messages-prives-publies-sur-la-timeline/mlix!MDk3LU0hjxIQ/'&gt;French newspaper Metro&lt;/a&gt; reported on Monday 24th September around 4pm (Paris time) a privacy problem regarding some posts published before 2010 displayed on the Facebook timeline of a few users. The latter posts were then thought to be old private messages that Facebook had involuntary made publicly available on the profiles of its users. The news was quickly relayed by other French and international newspapers and soon Facebook had to deal with an important critical situation about what was considered by users of the social platform as a bug endangering their privacy and intimacy. Now and very interestingly, all this was not due to a technical bug but to a profund deficiency of Facebook and its users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage of the development, it seems important to remind ourselves that the Timeline was introduced exactly one year ago at the F8 conference (September 22, 2011) and was since rolled out, first on a voluntary basis and then became the default Facebook profile. Note that one of the latest country where the Timeline was globally put in place is France. The principle of the Facebook Timeline is straightforward: to propose a kind of journal for every user of the social networking website, recomposing his/her life (eDNA) from birth to death. The Timeline is a pretty successfully completed information gathering tool which plays on our narcissism and rests on the Open Graph to collect a large amount of data about ourselves. The main issue I already emphasized in a &lt;a href='http://blog.florianbersier.com/etrust-homo-facebookiens/'&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; is that it tends to develop a model where the process of interacting online and sharing data is automatized in such a way that individuals are no longer accountable for their actions and are not aware of interacting anymore; this is what I call the Homo-Facebookiens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday&amp;#8217;s events highlighted very clearly the limits of the current &lt;a href='http://blog.florianbersier.com/etrust-homo-facebookiens/'&gt;Homo-Facebookiens&lt;/a&gt; model: you cannot build trust on interactions unawareness. Put otherwise, the trustor (i.e. a Facebook user) always needs to know when and how she/he interacts with the trustee (i.e. Facebook).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='this_is_not_a_bug'&gt;This is not a Bug&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, this is not a technical bug! Actually, the same &amp;#8220;issue&amp;#8221; had already been highlighted by a &lt;a href='http://translate.google.com/translate?sl=auto&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;js=n&amp;amp;prev=_t&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;amp;layout=2&amp;amp;eotf=1&amp;amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikropc.net%2Fkaikki_uutiset%2Farticle742440.ece'&gt;Finnish news site&lt;/a&gt; in December 2011. So the &amp;#8220;discovery&amp;#8221; of Metro France was nothing new. As stated by Facebook on the 24th of September:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small number of users raised concerns after what they mistakenly believed to be private messages appeared on their Timeline. Our engineers investigated these reports and found that the messages were older wall posts that had always been visible on the users’ profile pages. [&amp;#8230;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The private nature of some posts observed yesterday by Facebook users comes simply from the first model of communication Facebook was using before 2010, the so-called &amp;#8220;wall-to-wall&amp;#8221; conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='the_walltowall_conversations'&gt;The Wall-to-Wall conversations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, let&amp;#8217;s go back to the young years of Facebook! In those days, wall posts didn’t have comments, nor &amp;#8220;like&amp;#8221; buttons (see screenshot below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt='Facebook Wall-to-Wall Conversation' src='../img/facebook-wall.jpg' /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversations on the social platform were mainly powered by wall-to-wall conversations, e.g. I was writing something on your wall and you were replying on mine. Such communications were possibly more intimate than today because of the following two dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our friends&amp;#8217; network was smaller and less heterogenous back then.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;By its very nature, the fact to disseminate the flow of a conversation between the respective profiles of users X and Y was decreasing the probability for a user Z to get a whole picture of the conversation, if Z was only friend with X or Y.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id='the_database_architecture'&gt;The Database Architecture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, messages and wall posts are stored in two different databases, making extremely difficult any voluntary or involuntary manipulation that would lead to a mix of those two types of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed and as explained by a &lt;a href='http://news.ycombinator.org/item?id=4567009'&gt;Facebook employee&lt;/a&gt;, the messages backend is hbase-backed, designed for real-time communication more than history and the timeline backend is MySQL / C++ backed. Migrating data from hbase to MySQL would then have to take months of effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='_this_is_a_fail'&gt;&amp;#8230; This is a Fail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, this is definitely not a technical bug, but a conceptual bug/fail&amp;#8230; and a serious one which takes its roots in the way &lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/zuck'&gt;Mark Zuckerberg&lt;/a&gt; envisages social interactions, and especially &amp;#8220;privacy&amp;#8221;. Mark wants to build a platform able to become the repository of our lives online and offline, and to achieve this, he feels that our approach towards privacy must change. To make his message clearer, he even built a kind of provocative persona who is thought to not believe &lt;a href='http://www.wired.com/business/2010/04/report-facebook-ceo-mark-zuckerberg-doesnt-believe-in-privacy/'&gt;in privacy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I agree with Zuck that our definition of what is &amp;#8220;privacy&amp;#8221; must change [and has already changed thanks to Facebook, among others] if we wish to take full advantage of the Internet. However, the current way of enforcing such changes is not sustainable in the mid/long-term given its lack of respect, prospectiveness and transparency&amp;#8230; and what happened yesterday is a perfect illustration of the potential future problems of a Homo-Facebookiens model à la Zuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='transparency'&gt;Transparency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current vision at Facebook is that people will change their way of considering what is privacy by enforcing straightforward changes within the platform, e.g. the Timeline. This causation model is incomplete and lacks a crucial variable, i.e. transparency. Transparency means and implies that users are aware of the consequences of their actions within the platform, e.g. some Facebook users were not aware that old and possibly intimate posts were visible on their Facebook Timelines. Awareness of interacting is then necessary to trust, and trust will create a sustainable and natural basis for behavioral changes&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By omitting transparency, Facebook cannot guarantee trustworthy interactions within its own eco-system in the long-term, and so cannot develop a sound new paradigm for privacy. This leads me to the lack of prospectiveness of the Facebook method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='prospectiveness'&gt;Prospectiveness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prospectiveness or the fact to envisage the future effects of past and current decisions. Here, Facebook clearly did not take sufficiently into account the effects of its &amp;#8220;wall-to-wall&amp;#8221; conversations model on its current interaction model. This is not new&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='respect'&gt;Respect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Facebook business model is such that advertisers are the customers and Facebook users are the &amp;#8220;commodity&amp;#8221;. Given this economic configuration, it sometimes seems difficult for Facebook to remember that even if its users are not its prime customers, they are still crucial to its survival and should be handled carefully. Now, when facing this kind of crisis, it appears then good to invest a bit more time and energy concerning your PR. The official statement Facebook made about yesterday&amp;#8217;s events is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small number of users raised concerns after what they &lt;em&gt;mistakenly&lt;/em&gt; believed to be private messages appeared on their Timeline. Our engineers investigated these reports and found that the messages were older wall posts that had always been visible on the users&amp;#8217; profile pages. Facebook is &lt;em&gt;satisfied&lt;/em&gt; that there has been no breach of user privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phrased differently, our users are stupid and we cannot do anything about that! Even if this were true, there is certainly a better way to communicate about an issue that exists in the first place because of a conceptual fail, nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='the_commission_nationale_de_linformatique_et_des_liberts_cnil'&gt;The Commission nationale de l’informatique et des libertés (CNIL)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bug is currently investigated by the CNIL, an independent French administrative authority whose mission is to ensure that data privacy law is applied to the collection, storage, and use of personal data (&lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CNIL'&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;). The final report should be published in the coming days and available on the &lt;a href='http://www.cnil.fr/'&gt;CNIL official website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='resources'&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust is understood as a relation grounded on the trustor&amp;#8217;s beliefs about the trustee&amp;#8217;s capabilities (e.g. its reliability) and about the context in which the relation occurs. Trust implies then a trustor conscious of interacting with the trustee. This is a generalisation of the definition of trust provided by Gambetta; Gambetta, D. (1998), Can We Trust Trust?. In D. Gambetta (Ed.), Trust: Making and Breaking Cooperative Relations (213-238). Oxford: Basil Blackwell.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://thenextweb.com/facebook/2012/09/24/how-hide-old-wall-posts-public-private-facebook-timeline/'&gt;How to remove all your old Facebook wall posts, public or private, from your Timeline&lt;/a&gt; by TheNextWeb.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Implementation of Social Sharing into Jekyll</title>
   <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com/implementation-social-sharing-jekyll"/>
   <updated>2012-09-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.florianbersier.com/implementation-social-sharing-jekyll</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two common features of any blog are (i) a commenting system and (ii) some social sharing buttons. While the Jekyll Bootstrap provides natively a way to add a commenting provider (e.g. Disqus, LiveFyre, Facebook), it does not propose a simple way to add social sharing functionalities yet&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. This post aims at presenting a way of filling the latter gap&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read I did not manage to find any simple way of achieving it ;)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;All the code presented below can be found in my &lt;a href='https://github.com/xpressyoo/jekyll-bootstrap'&gt;forked version&lt;/a&gt; of the Jekyll Bootstrap on Github.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id='jekyll_configuration'&gt;Jekyll configuration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s start with the beginning, the Jekyll configuration file. I developed a new sharing section in the configuration file that allows to declare the sharing providers you want your blog to support (e.g. Twitter, Facebook, Google+) and the options (if any) necessary for the creation of the respective buttons. Here is how the &lt;strong&gt;new&lt;/strong&gt; sharing section of the configuration file looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;The _config.yml file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
[...]

    # Settings for sharing 
    # Sharing is for things like tweet, plusone, hn upvotes, like, linkedin
    # Add a tweet button 		=&gt; provider : tweet
    # Add a like button 		=&gt; provider : like (you also need a facebook appid)
    # Add a plus one button 	=&gt; provider : plusone
    # Add a HN button 		=&gt; provider : hn
    # Add them all (i.e. hn + tweet + plusone + like) =&gt; provider : all
    # Set 'provider' to the sharing provider you want to use.
    # Set 'provider' to false to turn sharing off globally.
    #
     sharing :
       provider : all
       twitter :
         size :
         via :
         count :
     facebook :
         appid : 123
         layout : button_count
         font :
         faces : false
         width : 90
     googleplus :
         size : medium
         width :
         annotation : bubble
     linkedin :
         counter : right      

[...]
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should be pretty straightforward. You just need to declare your provider of choice and enter some options if you want to override the default ones. Note that all the options follow the original syntax of the provider. For example, &lt;a href='https://developers.google.com/+/plugins/+1button/'&gt;Google +1 button options&lt;/a&gt; for &amp;#8220;size&amp;#8221; is [ small, medium, tall ] and for &amp;#8220;annotation&amp;#8221; is [ inline, bubble, none ].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='jekyll_bootstrap_includes'&gt;Jekyll Bootstrap Includes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second step I took was to modify the file named &lt;code&gt;sharing&lt;/code&gt; into the &lt;code&gt;_includes/JB/&lt;/code&gt; folder of the Jekyll Bootstrap installation. The latter file now redirects the provider&amp;#8217;s taxonomy used in the configuration file to the HTML file that generates the provider&amp;#8217;s sharing button(s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if &lt;code&gt;provider : like&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; then the &lt;code&gt;sharing&lt;/code&gt; file will include the &lt;code&gt;facebook&lt;/code&gt; HTML file present in &lt;code&gt;_includes/JB/sharing-providers/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;The sharing file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;{% if site.JB.sharing.provider and page.sharing != false %}

  {% case site.JB.sharing.provider %}
	{% when &amp;#39;like&amp;#39; %}
  		{% include JB/sharing-providers/facebook %}
	{% when &amp;#39;tweet&amp;#39; %}
  		{% include JB/sharing-providers/twitter %}
	{% when &amp;#39;plusone&amp;#39; %}
  		{% include JB/sharing-providers/googleplus %}
	{% when &amp;#39;linkedin&amp;#39; %}
  		{% include JB/sharing-providers/linkedin %}
	{% when &amp;#39;hn&amp;#39; %}
  		{% include JB/sharing-providers/hn %}
	{% when &amp;#39;all&amp;#39; %}
  		{% include JB/sharing-providers/global %}
  {% endcase %}

{% endif %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you note, this implies the creation of a new folder named &lt;code&gt;sharing-providers&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;_includes/JB/&lt;/code&gt;. This folder contains the diverse HTML files necessary to the generation of the sharing buttons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, this blog uses &lt;code&gt;provider : all&lt;/code&gt; which calls a file named &lt;code&gt;global&lt;/code&gt; looking as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;The global file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;fb-root&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;ul&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;post-share ulno mob&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Hacker News --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;hn&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;hnews&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Twitter --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;tw&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;https://twitter.com/share&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;twitter-share-button&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-text=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ page.title }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-via=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.twitter.via }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-related=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.author.twitter }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-count=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.twitter.count }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-size=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.twitter.size }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Tweet&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Google+ --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;gp&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;g-plusone&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-size=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.googleplus.size }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-annotation=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.googleplus.annotation }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-width=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.googleplus.width }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Facebook --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;fb&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;fb-like&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-send=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-layout=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.facebook.layout }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-width=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.facebook.width }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-show-faces=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.facebook.faces }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;data-font=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ site.JB.sharing.facebook.font }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Reddit --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;li&amp;gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='na'&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;http://www.reddit.com/buttonlite.js?i=4&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  
&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
 	
    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Async Social Buttons&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;fjs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;getElementsByTagName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='mi'&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;add&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='kd'&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='k'&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='k'&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;}&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;createElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class='nx'&gt;fjs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;parentNode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;insertBefore&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;fjs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='p'&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Twitter SDK&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nx'&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;twitter-wjs&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    
    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Google+ button&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nx'&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;https://apis.google.com/js/plusone.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    
    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Facebook SDK&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nx'&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;//connect.facebook.net/en_GB/all.js#xfbml=1&amp;amp;appId={{ site.JB.sharing.facebook.appid }}&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;facebook-jssdk&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    
    &lt;span class='c1'&gt;// Hacker News Button 	&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;hn_like&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nb'&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;createElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;iframe&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='nx'&gt;hn_like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;frameborder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;no&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='nx'&gt;hn_like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;scrolling&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;no&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='nx'&gt;hn_like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;28px&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='nx'&gt;hn_like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;110px&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='nx'&gt;hn_like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;http://hnlike.com/upvote.php?link=&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nb'&gt;encodeURIComponent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nb'&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;location&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;amp;title=&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class='o'&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nb'&gt;encodeURIComponent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;{{ page.title }}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='nx'&gt;hn_like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;innerHTML&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;iframes not supported by your browser&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      
      &lt;span class='kd'&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nx'&gt;where&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='o'&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='nb'&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s2'&gt;&amp;quot;hnews&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='nx'&gt;where&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;parentNode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nx'&gt;insertBefore&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;hn_like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class='nx'&gt;where&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class='p'&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class='p'&gt;}(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nb'&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='s1'&gt;&amp;#39;script&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='p'&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remark that the JavaScript is loaded asynchronously and that the option values of the configuration file are retrieved thanks to the Liquid markdown. The Hacker News button is powered by &lt;a href='http://hnlike.com/'&gt;hnlike.com&lt;/a&gt; and I was inspired by the Jekyll snippet proposed by &lt;a href='http://www.idryman.org/blog/2012/04/05/jekyll-octopress-hacker-news-plugin/'&gt;dryman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More examples of files can be found on my &lt;a href='https://github.com/xpressyoo/jekyll-bootstrap/tree/master/_includes/JB/sharing-providers'&gt;forked version&lt;/a&gt; of the Jekyll Bootstrap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='the_jekyll_theme'&gt;The Jekyll Theme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re almost done! The last step is to add the sharing buttons to your Jekyll theme. This is achieved by modifying the &lt;code&gt;post.html&lt;/code&gt; file present in &lt;code&gt;_includes/themes/name_of_your_theme&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;post.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;div class='highlight'&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class='html'&gt;[...]

    &lt;span class='c'&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Paste the 3 next lines where you want the sharing button(s) to appear --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class='na'&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='s'&gt;&amp;quot;post-sharing&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
     {% include JB/sharing %}
    &lt;span class='nt'&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;

[...]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s it, you&amp;#8217;re set!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Lettre Ouverte aux Candidats de l'Élection Présidentielle 2012</title>
   <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com/elysee-2012-hadopi"/>
   <updated>2012-01-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.florianbersier.com/elysee-2012-hadopi</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alors que le 6 mai approche à grands pas et que les campagnes respectives des candidats à la présidence de la République Française vont s&amp;#8217;intensifier dans les jours et semaines à venir, il semble opportun de proposer sous la forme d&amp;#8217;une lettre ouverte un ensemble de mesures traîtant de la place et de l&amp;#8217;utilisation du numérique dans une France et une Europe en crise, dans un monde en changement et dans une société humaine toujours plus connectée et digitale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parce que la loi Hadopi est l&amp;#8217;un des premiers projets tangibles (après la &lt;a href='http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000266350&amp;amp;dateTexte='&gt;loi DADVSI&lt;/a&gt; de 2006) du gouvernement français visant uniquement et spécifiquement Internet mais aussi parce que la création d&amp;#8217;une &amp;#8220;Haute autorité pour la diffusion des œuvres et la protection des droits sur Internet&amp;#8221; capture de manière évidente les problèmes engendrés par une volonté trop régulatrice d&amp;#8217;un Etat associée à une vision inadaptée et trop peu prospective de ce qu&amp;#8217;est le Net, il apparaît logique et naturel de débuter cette lettre par un argumentaire en faveur de l&amp;#8217;abrogation de Hadopi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='hadopi__quid'&gt;HADOPI - Quid?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La loi Hadopi ou loi &amp;#8220;Création Internet&amp;#8221; est une loi promulguée le 12 juin 2009 dont le but originel est de mettre un terme aux partages de fichiers en pair à pair (P2P) lorsque ces partages se font en infraction avec les droits d&amp;#8217;auteur. Elle se base sur une &amp;#8220;réponse graduée&amp;#8221; composée de trois étapes, deux étapes préventives puis éventuellement une étape finale répressive : d&amp;#8217;abord un courrier d&amp;#8217;avertissement par courriel, puis un courrier d&amp;#8217;avertissement par lettre recommandée, et enfin la suspension de l&amp;#8217;abonnement à l&amp;#8217;Internet pour une durée déterminée. Cette même loi crée une &amp;#8220;Haute Autorité pour la diffusion des œuvres et la protection des droits sur Internet&amp;#8221; dont elle tire son nom (Hadopi: &lt;a href='http://www.hadopi.fr/'&gt;www.hadopi.fr&lt;/a&gt;), autorité publique indépendante chargée de la surveillance des droits d&amp;#8217;auteur sur Internet. Voilà pour la brève description de ce qu&amp;#8217;est Hadopi, les paragraphes suivants ont pour intention de complèter ces quelques lignes en s&amp;#8217;attachant aux spécificités de la loi. (Source : &lt;a href='http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loi_Cr%C3%A9ation_et_Internet'&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='une_vision_trop_peu_prospective'&gt;Une Vision Trop Peu Prospective&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Un Modèle Économique Dépassé -&lt;/strong&gt; Le fondement d&amp;#8217;Hadopi, c&amp;#8217;est une vision remontant à l&amp;#8217;époque où les biens musicaux et vidéographiques étaient tous indivisibles, s&amp;#8217;échangeant uniquement sous forme physique (e.g. CD, DVD), et essentiellement exclusifs (payants). La loi tente d&amp;#8217;appliquer ce même modèle de distribution/consommation linéaire à des biens devenus digitaux et donc, par définition, devenus divisibles et non-exclusifs. Or, il est clair que cette vision hadopienne de la distribution musicale et vidéographique n&amp;#8217;est plus d&amp;#8217;actualité dans notre société digitale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pour citer Paul Krugman, prix Nobel d&amp;#8217;Economie 2008, &amp;#8220;Octet après octet, tout ce qui peut-être numérisé sera numérisé, rendant la propriété intellectuelle toujours plus facile à copier et toujours plus difficile à vendre plus cher qu&amp;#8217;un prix nominal. Et nous devrons trouver les modèles économiques et les modèles d&amp;#8217;affaires qui prennent cette réalité en compte&amp;#8221; (Source: &lt;a href='http://www.numerama.com/magazine/10833-le-nobel-d-economie-p-krugman-favorable-au-telechargement-gratuit.html'&gt;Numerama&lt;/a&gt;). L&amp;#8217;Internet tend en effet à créer une économie d&amp;#8217;abondance où les biens consommés ne doivent plus être comptés en unités mais en trafic estimé. C&amp;#8217;est pour cette raison qu&amp;#8217;il semble intéressant d&amp;#8217;encourager de nouveaux modèles économiques basés sur des systèmes de licence, de forfait, voire de publicité ciblée.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Un Modèle de Consommation Numérique Dépassé -&lt;/strong&gt; Comme déjà mentionné, le but originel d&amp;#8217;Hadopi est de protéger les droits d&amp;#8217;auteur en surveillant les échanges de fichiers (musique, vidéo) ayant lieu sur les réseaux P2P (peer-to-peer), c&amp;#8217;est-à-dire des réseaux informatiques où des ordinateurs interconnectés grâce à Internet jouent à la fois le rôle de client et de serveur. Cependant, il apparaît clairement en 2012 que le modèle P2P de consommation musicale et vidéographique n&amp;#8217;est plus à l&amp;#8217;ordre du jour. A l&amp;#8217;ère du &amp;#8221;&lt;a href='http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_computing'&gt;cloud computing&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;, de la fibre optique, du 4G et d&amp;#8217;un Internet toujours plus mobile et multi-support, de nouveaux modèles ont émergé et supplanté le P2P. Ces nouveaux modèles de consommation digitale ne se reposent ainsi plus sur la copie ou le téléchargement de fichiers entre deux ordinateurs mais sur la lecture en transit, sans téléchargment, de ces mêmes fichiers, id est le streaming. Pensez, par exemple, aux plateformes musicales telles que &lt;a href='http://www.spotify.com'&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='http://www.deezer.com'&gt;Deezer&lt;/a&gt; et &lt;a href='http://www.rara.com'&gt;Rara&lt;/a&gt; ou vidéographiques telles que &lt;a href='http://www.netflix.com'&gt;Netflix&lt;/a&gt;. Ces sites web basés sur un modèle économique dit de &lt;a href='http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freemium'&gt;freemium&lt;/a&gt; proposent &lt;a href='http://www.spotify.com/fr/work-with-us/labels-and-artists/'&gt;légalement&lt;/a&gt; de la musique et des films en streaming et les rendent disponibles sur une grande variété de supports grâce à des applications mobiles (e.g iPod, iPhone, Android, etc.) et/ou des appareils spécifiques (e.g. Apple TV, Google TV, Boxee Box, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L&amp;#8217;Hadopi ayant vu le vent tourner, l&amp;#8217;autorité a publié le 25 novembre dernier un &lt;a href='http://www.hadopi.fr/sites/default/files/page/pdf/CP_Hadopi_251111.pdf'&gt;communiqué&lt;/a&gt; où elle indiquait vouloir réfléchir à de nouveaux moyens pour protéger les droits d&amp;#8217;auteur sur les fichiers streamés. Bien que peu surprenant, ce communiqué ne fait que souligner et confirmer un peu plus les problèmes fondamentaux d&amp;#8217;Hadopi. Premièrement, il démontre encore et toujours un manque de vision à moyen/long terme. La consommation numérique de musique et vidéo converge rapidement vers des plateformes de streaming légales, qui protègent les droits d&amp;#8217;auteur en se basant sur de nouveaux modèles économiques, principalement freemium. S&amp;#8217;attaquer aux plateformes de streaming &amp;#8220;illégales&amp;#8221; est inutile dans le sens où de telles plateformes n&amp;#8217;arriveront de toute manière pas à survivre face à une concurrence faite de plateformes &amp;#8220;légales&amp;#8221; qui auront les moyens de proposer une offre toujours plus importante et de meilleure qualité. Pour résumer le premier problème, le manque de vision d&amp;#8217;Hadopi lui empêche de remarquer que dans un environnment de consommation numérique dynamique, légiférer est inefficace voire même contre-productif (cf. plus bas) et que l&amp;#8217;auto-régulation du marché est à terme la seule solution au problème de la protection des droits d&amp;#8217;auteur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='une_absurdit_technologique'&gt;Une Absurdité Technologique&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deuxièmement, ce communiqué renforce l&amp;#8217;une des principales critiques émises à l&amp;#8217;encontre de la loi, i.e. son manque de &amp;#8220;réalisme&amp;#8221; technologique qui rend son application délicate, voire difficile. En effet, que ce soit par l&amp;#8217;identification d&amp;#8217;utilisateurs P2P via leurs adresses IP, par le filtrage et blocage de serveurs de streaming sur le territoire français ou par la demande de coupure à l&amp;#8217;Internet, Hadopi pose le principe que la technologie a un caractère absolu, incontournable et indétournable. Or, une telle hypothèse est bien évidemment fausse. L&amp;#8217;identification d&amp;#8217;un contrevenant via une adresse IP est peu fiable pour la simple raison que ces adresses sont facilement falsifiables (e.g. &lt;a href='https://www.torproject.org/'&gt;TOR&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='http://www.hidemyass.com/'&gt;Proxy&lt;/a&gt;, VPN, &lt;a href='http://www.aircrack-ng.org/'&gt;WEP cracking&lt;/a&gt;) et ne garantissent donc pas le lien direct entre un individu et son adresse IP. De même, le blocage de serveurs de streaming (étrangers) allant à l&amp;#8217;encontre de la loi sera toujours une mesure inutile puisque contournable en adoptant une adresse IP non française (e.g. &lt;a href='http://www.hidemyass.com/'&gt;Proxy&lt;/a&gt;, VPN) ou en créant des sites miroirs (cf. affaire Wikileaks). Même inefficacité pour un blocage via &amp;#8220;take-down&amp;#8221; prévu par la Loi pour la Confiance dans l’Economie Numérique (&lt;a href='http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000801164&amp;amp;dateTexte='&gt;LCEN&lt;/a&gt;) de 2004 puisqu&amp;#8217;il suffira à un serveur de streaming d&amp;#8217;être hébergé dans un pays sans équivalent d&amp;#8217;Hadopi pour y échapper. Finalement, la sanction finale prévue par Hadopi qui n&amp;#8217;est autre que la coupure pure et simple de l&amp;#8217;accès à Internet du contrevenant est inconcevable dans un pays ou la connexion à l&amp;#8217;Internet fait presque toujours partie de packages &amp;#8220;téléphone-télévision-Internet&amp;#8221;. Demander la coupure de l&amp;#8217;accès au réseau à un FAI reviendrait dans beaucoup de cas à couper également l&amp;#8217;accès au téléphone et à la télévision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='le_risque_du_toujours_plus'&gt;Le Risque du &amp;#8220;Toujours Plus&amp;#8221;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troisièmement, le communiqué du 25 novembre 2011 cristallise l&amp;#8217;un des principaux dangers de légiférer en faveur d&amp;#8217;une surveillance et/ou régulation de l&amp;#8217;Internet: le besoin d&amp;#8217;aller toujours plus loin. En effet, dans un environnement changeant tel que le net, le législateur doit constamment s&amp;#8217;adapter, au risque de devenir trop oppressant et -volontairement ou involontairement- d&amp;#8217;étouffer de son poids le flux d&amp;#8217;échanges numériques. L&amp;#8217;Hadopi, en passant du P2P au streaming, en est l&amp;#8217;exemple parfait. Faisant face à de nouveaux mécanismes d&amp;#8217;échanges, la haute autorité doit choisir d&amp;#8217;autres variables d&amp;#8217;action dont le nombre est extrêmement limité et converge vers une seule direction: le filtrage et le blocage de l&amp;#8217;Internet. Hors, une telle dérive signerait, à moyen terme, l&amp;#8217;arrêt de mort de l&amp;#8217;Internet français. Pourquoi cela?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le fait d&amp;#8217;instaurer un filtrage du réseau implique, tout d&amp;#8217;abord, que toutes les données doivent passer par quelques points de passage définis et obligatoires, diminuant ainsi le débit et le flux de ces mêmes données à travers le réseau - ce qui pourrait aller jusqu&amp;#8217;à une saturation du réseau français en cas d&amp;#8217;extrême centralisation du routage du trafic. Le fait de proposer une infrastructure de moins bonne qualité conjugué à un filtrage de certains types de contenus decourageront dans un second temps l&amp;#8217;innovation et affaibliront la croissance économique du pays. Enfin, un réseau filtré sera plus sujet aux pannes et attaques à cause d&amp;#8217;une architecture proposant un nombre amoindri de points d&amp;#8217;entrée et de sortie du trafic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il est important de rappeler que la force d&amp;#8217;un réseau tel qu&amp;#8217;Internet réside dans le fait qu&amp;#8217;il est, par définition, un réseau ouvert et neutre. Son ouverture associée à sa neutralité sont les deux valeurs essentielles qui ont garanti, garantissent et garantiront le succès du net et sa valeur pour la société humaine. Le fait qu&amp;#8217;un gouvernement fasse pression sur des fournisseurs d&amp;#8217;accès à Internet (FAI) pour surveiller et contrôler les échanges qui se passent au sein du réseau vont directement à l&amp;#8217;encontre de ces 2 principes de base reconnus et défendus par l&amp;#8217;&lt;a href='http://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/fr/pressroom/content/20111117IPR31726/html/Internet-doit-rester-ouvert-et-neutre'&gt;Union Européenne&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='une_loi_indigne_du_pays_des_droits_de_lhomme'&gt;Une Loi indigne du Pays des Droits de l&amp;#8217;Homme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quatrièmement, l&amp;#8217;Hadopi est par quelques-uns des ses aspects en contradiction avec les valeurs républicaines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coupure de l&amp;#8217;Accès à Internet -&lt;/strong&gt; L&amp;#8217;une des sanctions finales décidées par l&amp;#8217;autorité judiciaire qui doit punir l&amp;#8217;internaute ayant ignoré les avertissements préalables pour du téléchargement illégal ou un défaut de sécurisation de son accès Internet est la coupure pure et son simple de son accès au réseau. Or, dans une société ou l&amp;#8217;Internet est de plus en plus présent dans la vie des citoyens et de plus en plus nécessaire à l&amp;#8217;execution des échanges sociaux et économiques du quotidien, et où il tend à devenir le principal portail de la connaissance (e.g. bibliothèques et médiathèques numériques), interdire son accès va à l&amp;#8217;encontre à la fois des valeurs de la République et du &amp;#8220;droit à l&amp;#8217;accès à la connaissance pour tous&amp;#8221; consacré par l&amp;#8217;ONU, le Conseil de l&amp;#8217;Europe et la France (entre autres). Sans aller jusqu&amp;#8217;à l&amp;#8217;inscription de l&amp;#8217;accès à l&amp;#8217;Internet comme un droit de l&amp;#8217;Homme, la technologie étant un catalyseur de droits, pas un droit en elle-même pour paraphraser Vinton Cerf, père fondateur de l&amp;#8217;Internet (&amp;#8220;technology is an enabler of rights, not a right itself&amp;#8221; &lt;a href='http://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/05/opinion/internet-access-is-not-a-human-right.html'&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt; - Janvier 2012), l&amp;#8217;Hadopi va clairement à l&amp;#8217;encontre des droits primaires de chaque Homme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il est également intéressant de noter que dans son &lt;a href='http://www.article19.org/data/files/pdfs/reports/report-of-the-special-rapporteur-on-the-promotion-and-protection-of-the-righ.pdf'&gt;rapport de mai 2011&lt;/a&gt; sur la promotion et la protection du droit de la liberté d&amp;#8217;opinion et d&amp;#8217;expression, l&amp;#8217;ONU &amp;#8221;s&amp;#8217;alarme des propositions qui visent à déconnecter l&amp;#8217;utilisateur d&amp;#8217;Internet lorsqu&amp;#8217;il violent les droits de propriété intellectuelle. Cela inclut les législations basées sur le concept de riposte graduée qui imposent une série de sanctions et qui peuvent mener à la suspension de la fourniture de la connexion Internet comme la riposte graduée en France ou le Digital Economy Act 2010 en Grande-Bretagne&amp;#8221; Chapitre D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Présomption de culpabilité -&lt;/strong&gt;Hadopi repose sur la &lt;a href='http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loi_Cr%C3%A9ation_et_Internet#Pr.C3.A9somption_de_culpabilit.C3.A9'&gt;présomption de culpabilité&lt;/a&gt;, c&amp;#8217;est-à-dire que la charge de la preuve est portée sur le demandeur. Or, dans un pays où la présemption d&amp;#8217;innocence est reconnue depuis la Déclaration des droits de l&amp;#8217;homme et du citoyen du 26 août 1789 et où &amp;#8220;tout homme est présumé innocent jusqu&amp;#8217;à ce qu&amp;#8217;il ait été déclaré coupable&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;, il est clair que la démarche juridique d&amp;#8217;Hadopi va à l&amp;#8217;encontre des fondements de la République.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protection de la Vie Privée -&lt;/strong&gt; Que ce soit par l&amp;#8217;introduction de mouchards dans les ordinateurs de contrevenants ou par la volonté affichée de surveiller le trafic s&amp;#8217;écoulant à travers Internet, Hadopi représente un danger certain pour la protection des données personnelles et de la sphère privée.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='conclusion'&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parce que les lois Hadopi sont basées sur des modèles économiques et numériques dépassés, reposent sur des moyens de surveillance, de contrôle et de punition contournables et inapplicables, mettent en péril l&amp;#8217;ouverture et la neutralité de l&amp;#8217;Internet, limitent et découragent l&amp;#8217;innovation et la croissance économique et vont à l&amp;#8217;encontre des valeurs républicaines, il apparaît important et nécessaire de proposer une abrogation de ces dernières.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finalement, dans un monde fait de gouvernments qui tendent à mettre de plus en plus en danger la Neutralité et l&amp;#8217;ouverture de l&amp;#8217;Internet, et en ce faisant, à limiter de plus en plus les libertés de leur citoyens (e.g. Projet &lt;a href='http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_Online_Piracy_Act'&gt;SOPA&lt;/a&gt; aux USA), le fait d&amp;#8217;abroger Hadopi semble être une décision courageuse et économiquement intéressante. En effet, cela enverrait premièrement un message clair à la communauté internationale, montrant que la France se pose en porte-drapeau de la défense de la Neutralité du Net, redorant ainsi l&amp;#8217;image du pays des Droits de l&amp;#8217;Homme dans le monde. Deuxièmement, le fait de garantir et défendre un Internet neutre et ouvert redonnerait un avantage comparatif à la France, attirerait les talents du monde tech et favoriserait l&amp;#8217;innovation et la croissance.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Primaires Socialistes en France</title>
   <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com/primaires-socialistes"/>
   <updated>2011-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.florianbersier.com/primaires-socialistes</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A quatre jours des primaires du parti socialiste, j&amp;#8217;ai décidé de prendre un peu de temps pour analyser la présence web des six candidats que sont Mme Aubry, Mme Royal, M. Baylet, M. Hollande, M. Montebourg et M. Valls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='ps__open_source_'&gt;PS = Open Source ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En parcourant leurs différents sites web, j&amp;#8217;ai été tout d&amp;#8217;abord agréablement surpris d&amp;#8217;observer que tous utilisaient des CMS (Content Management Systems) Open Source. Les sites de Royal, Valls et Baylet sont ainsi sous &lt;a href='http://wordpress.org'&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt; alors que ceux de Aubry, Hollande et Montebourg sont sous &lt;a href='http://drupal.org'&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt;, 3 versus 3 =&amp;gt; parfaite égalité.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='montremoi_ton_site_et_je_te_dirai_qui_tu_es'&gt;Montre-moi ton site et je te dirai qui tu es&amp;#8230;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='jeanmichel_baylet__a_la_trane_'&gt;Jean-Michel Baylet : A la Traîne ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.jeanmichelbaylet.fr'&gt;Jean-Michel Baylet&lt;/a&gt; propose un site très décevant avec peu d&amp;#8217;identité expliqué par un thème WordPress extrêmement basique, un graphisme &amp;#8216;amateur&amp;#8217;, une intégration sociale pauvre (juste Facebook) et beaucoup trop de plugins de mauvaise qualité. Le site ne comprend pas de Favicon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='manuel_valls__agressif_'&gt;Manuel Valls : Agressif ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le constat n&amp;#8217;est guère plus brillant pour &lt;a href='http://valls2012.org'&gt;Manuel Valls&lt;/a&gt;, malgré un thème WordPress plus travaillé et une intégration sociale plus complète. On se sentira agressé par la vidéo en auto-play à la &amp;#8216;Eurovision&amp;#8217;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='franois_hollande__stress'&gt;François Hollande : Stressé?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Très déçu également par le site de &lt;a href='http://francoishollande.fr'&gt;François Hollande&lt;/a&gt; qui propose un design très peu aéré où le visiteur se sentira perdu (voire oppressé) parmi la quantité d&amp;#8217;informations. On notera également que le site n&amp;#8217;a été développé que pour des écrans de plus 1280px de largeur. A l&amp;#8217;ère des tablettes et des netbooks, on aurait pu faire mieux. Bon point cependant pour la sidebar qui est très réussie malgré le widget standard Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='arnaud_montebourg__superficiel_'&gt;Arnaud Montebourg : Superficiel ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le site d&amp;#8217;&lt;a href='http://www.arnaudmontebourg2012.fr'&gt;Arnaud Montebourg&lt;/a&gt; est sobre et organisé. Cependant, au fur et à mesure que le visiteur s&amp;#8217;approche du footer, s&amp;#8217;installe une impression de vide et/ou de manque de contenu - à l&amp;#8217;inverse de M. Hollande. Clairement, quelques widgets présents dans la sidebar auraient dû être placés dans la colonne centrale et le footer aurait dû être plus travaillé afin d&amp;#8217;éviter cette impression. On notera le logo de campagne très réussi. Arnaud Montebourg est également le seul candidat à proposer un site optimisé où les fichiers et le nombre de requêtes sont minimisés.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='sgolne_royal__gentillette_'&gt;Ségolène Royal : Gentillette ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.segoleneroyal2012.fr'&gt;Ségolène Royal&lt;/a&gt; propose un site au design aéré et très arrondi, voire même gentillet. La typographie serif se marie mal avec le design général et une attention plus importante aurait dû être apportée aux textes qui sont souvent coupés. Finalement, le site est agréable à l&amp;#8217;oeil mais ne donne pas envie de consulter son contenu. A noter le soin apporté aux réseaux sociaux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='martine_aubry__equilibre_'&gt;Martine Aubry : Equilibrée ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.martineaubry.fr'&gt;Martine Aubry&lt;/a&gt; propose à mon avis le site le plus équilibré et réussi de tous les candidats. En effet, malgré un contenu important, le design reste aéré et donc les informations faciles à lire. On notera également l&amp;#8217;utilisation intelligente des réseaux sociaux ainsi qu&amp;#8217;un footer extrêmement sympathique à l&amp;#8217;oeil. Le logo de campagne aurait mérité plus de travail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='montremoi_ta_epopularit_et_je_te_dirai_si_tu_gagneras'&gt;Montre-moi ta e-Popularité et je te dirai si tu gagneras&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='sur_facebook'&gt;Sur Facebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nombre de supporters ou fans Facebook des candidats:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ségolène Royal (création: 9 août 2009) &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; . . 30&amp;#8217;010&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Martine Aubry (création: 7 janvier 2010) &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; . . 16&amp;#8217;194&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Arnaud Montebourg (création: 11 juillet 2008) &amp;#8230; . 14&amp;#8217;028&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;François Hollande (création: 15 février 2011) &amp;#8230; . . 13&amp;#8217;670&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Manuel Valls (création: inconnue) &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; . 6&amp;#8217;692&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Jean-Michel Baylet (création: 11 décembre 2008) &amp;#8230; 798&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nota Bene: Le terme &amp;#8220;création&amp;#8221; indique la date de création supposée de la page Facebook en se basant sur la date d&amp;#8217;upload de la première photo de profil sur la page du candidat. Données recueillies dans la nuit du 4 au 5 octobre.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M. Montebourg est le premier candidat à avoir créé la page Facebook utilisée actuellement pour sa campgane. Cette remarque pourrait expliquer son score assez élevé qui le met en 3ème place. Le même raisonnement ainsi que sa popularité post 2007 pourrait également expliquer le nombre relativement élevé de fans de Mme Royal sur Facebook. A noter l&amp;#8217;excellent score du dernier candidat venu sur Facebook, i.e. M. Hollande, qui talonne M. Montebourg et n&amp;#8217;est pas loin de Mme Aubry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='sur_twitter'&gt;Sur Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nombre de followers Twitter des candidats:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;François Hollande (création: 9 janvier 2009) &amp;#8230; . 28&amp;#8217;235&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Martine Aubry (création: 23 mars 2009) &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; . 21&amp;#8217;143&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Arnaud Montebourg (création: 27 août 2009)&amp;#8230; . 20&amp;#8217;917&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Ségolène Royal (création: 26 août 2009) &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; 20&amp;#8217;726&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Manuel Valls (création: 31 août 2009) &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; 6&amp;#8217;066&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Jean-Michel Baylet (création: 21 juin 2011) &amp;#8230; . . 1&amp;#8217;310&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nota Bene: Le terme &amp;#8220;création&amp;#8221; indique la date de création du compte Twitter en se basant sur les résultats du site &lt;a href='www.whendidyoujointwitter.com'&gt;WhenDidYouJoinTwitter.com&lt;/a&gt;. Données recueillies dans la nuit du 4 au 5 octobre.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A noter que 2009 semble avoir été l&amp;#8217;année découverte de Twitter par les éléphants du PS, le pionner étant François Hollande. M. Hollande apparaît clairement d&amp;#8217;ailleurs comme le favori en terme de followers sur Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='sur_google'&gt;Sur Google+&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concernant le dernier venu sur les réseaux sociaux. Les différents candidats sont dans les cercles de:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ségolène Royal (création: 20 juillet 2011) &amp;#8230; . . 9&amp;#8217;287&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;François Hollande (création: 12 août 2011)&amp;#8230; . 8&amp;#8217;491&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Martine Aubry (création: 17 août 2011) &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; 8&amp;#8217;119&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Arnaud Montebourg &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; . . N/A&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Manuel Valls &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; .&amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; .&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; . N/A&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Jean-Michel Baylet &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; &amp;#8230; N/A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nota Bene: Le terme &amp;#8220;création&amp;#8221; indique la date de publication du premier post sur Google+. Données recueillies dans la nuit du 4 au 5 octobre.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A noter que seulement la moitié des candidats a trouvé bon d&amp;#8217;ouvrir un compte sur Google+. Mme Royal a créé son compte un mois avant ses &amp;#8220;rivaux&amp;#8221; du moment et profite ainsi d&amp;#8217;une légère avance, certainement pas significative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='google_search'&gt;Google Search&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Un indice de popularité intéressant est également le nombre de requêtes sur les moteurs de recherche pour les noms des différents candidats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En utilisant les résultats de &lt;a href='http://www.google.com/insights/search'&gt;Google Insight For Search&lt;/a&gt; pour Google France sur les 30 derniers jours, i.e. le mois de septembre, on obtient le classement suivant :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;François Hollande&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;..44&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Martine Aubry&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;33&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Ségolène Royal&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;..25&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Arnaud Montebourg&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;..19&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Manuel Valls&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;.17&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Jean-Michel Baylet&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;..3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;François Hollande apparaît comme le candidat le plus recherché sur Google France lors du dernier mois, viennent ensuite Martine Aubry et Ségolène Royal. Il est intéressant de remarquer que l&amp;#8217;écart entre les candidats Aubry et Hollande semble s’agrandir ces derniers jours (voir graphique ci-dessous), et cela en faveur de François Hollande.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt='Primaires PS 2011, Google Insight Graph' src='http://api.ning.com/files/lpNlXgY2BuRVGUmCUeHoQXhfJJ-LCfVgHEfwAfIs3qbyR9cScTShpGOfsYJV2D0MvH1R-GDBuMO6bjdiGFYRdDvGIJ0SDCeV/chartprimaires.png?width=750' /&gt;
&lt;h4 id='par_rgions_martine_aubry_versus_franois_hollande'&gt;Par Régions, Martine Aubry versus François Hollande&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorsque l&amp;#8217;on ne considère que les deux favoris des primaires et qu&amp;#8217;on découpe les résultats par région, on observe que M. Hollande devance Mme Aubry partout sauf en Auvergne et Midi-Pyrénées. L&amp;#8217;écart est particulièrement important en Île de France et Poitou-Charentes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt='Primaires PS 2011, par Régions' src='http://api.ning.com/files/lpNlXgY2BuR2pE6Ln5S2ty*AnKFwcos5v8bUmBT64aVG7d7oHhjRY9wmrOTLN-riGZObfBmOGUdDMfvmByBq9CxT6mDCVJ5Q/regions.png' /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nota Bene: Données recueillies pour toutes les configurations possibles des noms complets des différents candidats, ex. &amp;#8220;francois hollande&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;françois hollande&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;hollande françois&amp;#8221;, etc. Les nombres ci-dessus indiquent la quantité de recherches ayant été effectuées pour un nom de candidat donné, par rapport au nombre total de recherches effectuées sur Google au cours de la même période. Ils ne représentent pas le volume de recherche en valeur absolue, car les données sont normalisées et présentées sur une échelle allant de 0 à 100.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='conclusions'&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Après analyse de leurs présences et stratégies web, Montebourg, Royal, Aubry et Hollande apparaissent clairement comme les candidats aux primaires les plus actifs et impliqués sur la toile française.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintenant, si on observe leur popularité sur les différents grands réseaux sociaux ainsi que les statistiques de recherche, il semble que le web français tende à désigner un vainqueur, François Hollande, suivi de Martine Aubry et Ségolène Royal. A confirmer le 9 octobre prochain&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How Homo-Facebookiens will kill Homo-Sapiens?</title>
   <link href="http://blog.florianbersier.com/etrust-homo-facebookiens"/>
   <updated>2011-09-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.florianbersier.com/etrust-homo-facebookiens</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I will start this post with a simple question: How much of your daily time spent on the Web is spent on Google products or Facebook? A very large proportion I presume and this should not be very surprising since the Internet favourites a winner-takes-the-most scheme, i.e. a market in which only an extremely small number of players can survive economic competition, the winning player taking all the market-share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, two big &amp;#8216;survivors&amp;#8217; that are Facebook and Google are engaged in a bloody battle in which the weapons are ways to gather more information/data about their users. More than never, the Summer and early Fall have made obvious this information war and the &amp;#8216;weapons&amp;#8217; used. Think of Google+&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, Google Wallet&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, Google Offers&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, Facebook Timeline&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;, Facebook Open Graph&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the main casualties of this war will be, at the end, us, their users and the Internet in general, I feel the need to share my viewpoint about the direction or vision those two companies want to impose to the Internet and the dangers they represent for our (e)Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what follows, I will focus on Facebook, more precisely on the Facebook post-F8. Why this choice? 1) Articles about F8 are trendy :) 2) F8 parametrizes well the dangers of the info-war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you just came back to Earth and missed &lt;strike&gt;yesterday's&lt;/strike&gt; Facebook conference called F8 on the 22nd of September, here is a summary of the main changes the social platform has already put in place or is going to implement in the next few days/weeks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new Profile, the “Facebook Timeline”: &lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/about/timeline'&gt;https://www.facebook.com/about/timeline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;A better and “smarter” Open Graph: &lt;a href='https://developers.facebook.com/docs/beta/'&gt;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/beta/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be concise, the latter two changes have the potential to transform deeply how nearly 1 billion individuals&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; will interact online, by making the amount of information about people more open/visible, more precise and more important, and by making our interactions more integrated and inclusive to our (digital) lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On paper, this sounds exciting and those new features are surely impressive and well-thought both on the front-end side and back-end. Nevertheless, they ask, in my opinion, several important questions. Since I want to keep this post short, I will only highlight two of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we build eTrust by making interactions unconscious?&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;How do we ensure eTrust by leaving an increasing amount of data in the hands of a unique private company, without any satisfying external controlling organization?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id='etrust'&gt;eTrust&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='why_do_we_need_trust_or_why_does_a_society_offline_or_online_need_trust'&gt;Why do we need trust or why does a society (offline or online) need trust?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his analysis of trust, Luhmann&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; brings certainly the most appropriate and concise answer to such issues by stating that “trust is an effective form of complexity reduction”. Put otherwise, the need of trust rests on the fact that trust is a starting point for the derivation of rules for ‘good’ conduct, or for ways of acting ‘successfully’ by decreasing complexity, risk and uncertainty in a given (social) system. Now, it remains to understand what is (e)Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='what_is_etrust_or_equivalently_online_trust'&gt;What is eTrust, or equivalently online trust?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s simply the driving force of any digital interaction. Put differently, Trust is often understood as a relation between an agent (e.g. a Facebook user) and another agent or object (e.g. Facebook). The relation is supposed to be grounded on the truster’s beliefs about the trustee’s capabilities (e.g. its reliability) and about the context in which the relation occurs. This is a generalisation of the definition of trust provided by Gambetta&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust implies then a truster conscious of interacting with the trustee.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='the_interaction_awareness_issue'&gt;The Interaction Awareness Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Open Graph&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; presented @F8 has been developed in the aim of increasing the amount of data exchanged and stored by Facebook. However, Open Graph&amp;#8217;s new features have in my opinion a very perverse side-effect by making people unconscious of interacting online. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be concise, the Open Graph protocol allows 3rd party web sites to use the Facebook platform to engage with their users on Facebook and possibly increase their audience / set of interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new features of this protocol rest on a “user → action → object” model. This means that whenever a Facebook user installs a 3rd party application, every interaction he or she will have with this 3rd party platform will be automatically stored by Facebook and attached to his or her profile/identity. For example, let&amp;#8217;s say that I have the Spotify application installed, then everything I will listen to in Spotify will be potentially available to my Facebook friends and then Facebook. Same reasoning applies to what I read / eat&amp;#8230; You see the problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 2steps mechanisms blurs and even erases the awareness of interacting in a specific context by playing on the large amount of digital interactions we make everyday. Then, how is it possible to develop a trustworthy Web when people are not even aware of interacting&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='the_data_collection_issue'&gt;The Data Collection Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an application developer for Facebook, I had the opportunity to put my hands on the new &amp;#8220;timeline profile&amp;#8221; on the 22nd of September. If you are curious, you can do the same by following a step-by-step tutorial written by Greg Kumparak (TechCrunch)&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once my “timeline profile” set, my very first impression was this one: “OMG! The UI (User Interface) design is great. WTF! How can they think that I&amp;#8217;ll be willing to post a photo of me as a baby, the name of my dog, something on a lost loved one or when I overcame an illness&amp;#8230;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is that by having developed an intuitive UI, by leaving the possibility to their users to even publish more information on their lives and by playing on our narcissism and their immense community, the guys at Facebook have found a great way to gather relatively easily (even) more information about their users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to this the naughty consequences of the new Open Graph mentioned previously and you have an almost perfect data-collection-weapon. The result is simple and not new: an extremely large amount of information about us: from basic ID details to very private ones with precise and detailed information about our preferences, interests and habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is new though, it&amp;#8217;s the ability of recomposing very precisely our (digital) DNA, i.e. what we are, or at least the convergence towards a desire of recomposing automatically our DNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, our approach to the privacy must change in the digital age and already changed thanks to Facebook and Google, among others. I think this change was necessary to pursue the development of the Internet and then my point here is not to say like some that we should &amp;#8220;boycott online platforms that gather data about ourselves&amp;#8221;, clearly not. What I think important is again to be conscious or aware of the amount of data we make available on the Web and to whom we make it available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this respect, the new Facebook represents a potential danger by automatizing the process of interacting online / sharing data and by making individuals no longer accountable for their actions, it&amp;#8217;s what I call the Homo-Facebookiens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a bit paradoxical to observe our current democratic societies reacting strongly (sometimes with reason) whenever a government puts in place a way to gather more data about its citizens when the same citizens share (overall) even more data with companies such as Facebook or Google, &lt;i&gt;id est&lt;/i&gt; by definition entities that do not follow a democratic structure and cannot be controlled by their users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to a simple and straightforward question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to ensure a trustworthy and sane development of the Internet in particular and of our Society in general when our &amp;#8216;DNA&amp;#8217; will be in the hands of a very few powerful companies?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a question will need to be addressed in a near future in order to ensure that those great companies/ideas that are Google and Facebook (&amp;#8230; and alike) will continue to expand our common knowledge and make the Homo Sapiens a better human being, and not the reverse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, your reactions are welcome and encouraged below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://plus.google.com/'&gt;https://plus.google.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.google.com/wallet/'&gt;http://www.google.com/wallet/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.google.com/offers/'&gt;https://www.google.com/offers/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://developers.facebook.com/docs/beta/'&gt;https://www.facebook.com/about/timeline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.google.com/wallet/'&gt;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/beta/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.facebook.com/press/info.php?statistics'&gt;http://www.facebook.com/press/info.php?statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://techcrunch.com/2011/09/22/how-to-enable-facebook-timeline/'&gt;http://techcrunch.com/2011/09/22/how-to-enable-facebook-timeline/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Luhmann, N. (1979), Trust and Power. Chichester: John Wiley.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Gambetta, D. (1998), Can We Trust Trust?. In D. Gambetta (Ed.), Trust: Making and Breaking Cooperative Relations (213-238). Oxford: Basil Blackwell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>